[Music]
a co-founder of the social news and
entertainment website reddit has been
found dead he certainly was a prodigy
although he never kind of thought of
himself like that
he was totally unexcited about studying
businesses and making money there's a
profound sense of loss tonight in
Highland Park Aaron Swartz
as loved ones say goodbye to one of the
Internet's brightest lights open access
and computer activists are mourning his
loss
an astonishing intellect you talked to
people who knew that he was killed by
the government and MIT betrayed all of
its basic principles they wanted to make
an example out of him okay
governments have an insatiable desire to
control he was potentially facing 35
years in prison and a 1 million dollar
fine raising questions of prosecutorial
zeal and I would say even misconduct
have you looked into that particular
matter and reached any conclusions
[Music]
growing up you know I slowly had this
process of realized that you know all
the things around me that people had
told me were just the natural way things
were the way things always would be
you weren't natural at all they were
things that could be changed and they
were things that more importantly were
wrong and should change and once I
realized that there was really kind of
no going back well he was born in
Highland Park and grew up here and came
from a family of three brothers all
extorting any type so we were all you
know not the best behaved children you
know three boys running around all the
time
causing trouble but I've come to the
realization Aaron learned how to learn
at a very young age he knew what he
wanted and he always wanted to do it he
always accomplished what he wanted his
curiosity was endless
[Music]
one day he said to Susan what's this
free family entertainment downtown
repair it was three at the time she said
what are you talking about is that look
it says here in the refrigerator
three family entertainment and downtown
hello hi Arkansas
she was floored and astonished that he
could I pulled a book off the shelf that
was from like 1900 and showed in I said
you know this is really just an
extraordinary place we all were curious
children but Aaron really liked learning
and really liked teaching I remember he
came home from his first algebra class
he was like Noah let me teach you
algebra I'm like what is algebra he was
always like that
[Music]
when he was about 2 or 3 years old and
Bob introduced him to computers then he
just took off like crazy on them we all
had computers but Aaron really took to
them really took to the Internet
[Music]
he started programming from a really
young age I remember the first program
that I wrote with him was in basic and
it was a Star Wars trivia game he's sat
down with me in the basement where the
computer was for hours programming this
game
the problem that I kept having with him
is there is nothing that I wanted done
and to him it there was always something
to do always something that programming
could solve the way Aaron always find is
that programming is Magic rate you can
accomplish these things that normal
humans can't Aaron made an ATM using
like a Macintosh in like a cardboard box
one one year for Halloween I didn't know
what I wanted to be and he thought it'd
be really really cool if I dressed up
like his new favorite computer which at
the time was the original iMac I mean he
hated dressing up for Halloween but he
loved convincing other people to dress
up his things that he wanted to see he
made this website called the info where
people can just fill in information like
I'm sure someone out there knows all
about gold gold leafing why don't they
write about that on this website and
then other people could come at a later
point and read those read that
information and and edit the information
if they thought it was bad not too
dissimilar from Wikipedia right and this
was this was before Wikipedia had begun
and this was developed by a 12 year old
in his room by himself running on you
know this tiny server using ancient
technology and one of the teachers
response like this is a terrible idea
that you can't just like let anyone
author the diction like author the
encyclopedia the whole reason we have
scholars is to write these books for us
how did you ever have such a terrible
idea me and my other brother would be
like oh you know yeah what competing is
cool but we had
I was like five years ago aaron's
website the info org wins a school
competition hosted by the
cambridge-based web design firm
arsdigita we all went to cambridge for
the when he won the arsdigita prize and
you know we had no clue what aaron was
doing it was obvious that the prize was
really important aaron soon became
involved with online programming
communities then in the process of
shaping a new tool for the web he comes
up to me it's like Ben this is really
awesome thing that I'm working at you
need to hear about it I'm like yeah what
is it says it's this thing called RSS
and he explains to me what RSS is I'm
like like why is that useful Aaron like
is any site using it like what why would
I want to use it there is this mailing
list for people who are working on RSS
and XML more generally and there was a
there's a person on it named Aaron
Swartz who was combative but very smart
and who had lots of good ideas and he
didn't ever come to the face-to-face
meetings and they said you know are you
when are you gonna come out to one of
these face-to-face meetings and he said
you know I don't think my mom would let
me I you know I'm from 14 yo just turned
14 and so their first reaction was well
you know this person is colleague we've
been working with all year is that was
13 years old while we were working with
him and he's only 14 now and their
second reaction was nice P really want
to meet him
you know that's extraordinary and he was
part of the committee that drafted RSS
what he was doing was to help build the
plumbing for modern hypertext the piece
that he was working on RSS was a tool
that you can use to get summaries of
things that are going on in other web
pages most commonly you would use this
for a blog you might have 10 or 20
people's blogs you want to read use that
RSS feeds these summaries of what's
going on on those other pages to create
a unified list of all the stuff that's
going on Aaron was really young
but he he understood the technology and
he saw that it was imperfect it looked
always to help make it better
[Music]
says mom started bundling him on planes
and Chicago we'd pick him up in San
Francisco we'd introduce him to
interesting people to argue with and
we'd marvel at his horrific eating
habits he only ate white food only like
you know steamed rice and not fried rice
because that wasn't sufficiently white
and white bread and and and so on and
you know you kind of marvel at this the
quality of the debate emerging from this
what appeared to be a small boys milk
and you think you know this is a kid
who's really gonna go somewhere if he
doesn't die of scurvy let's hold dog
food dog food over cellphones but
there's still a lot of innovation going
on I think if you don't see the
innovation maybe your head isn't listen
he takes on this an alpha nerd
personality where he's sort of like I'm
smarter than you because I'm smarter
than you I'm better than you and I can
tell you what to do it's an extension of
like him being kind of like
like searching for aliens or trying to
cure cancer first minimal IRC or
Internet Relay Chat he didn't just write
code he also sort of got people got
people excited about solving problems he
got he was like he was a connector the
free culture movement has had a lot of
his energy I think and I was trying to
make the world work he was trying to fix
it he had a very kind of strong
personality that definitely ruffled
feathers at times it wasn't necessarily
the case that he was always comfortable
in the world and the world wasn't always
comfortable with him Aaron got into High
School and was really just sick of
school he didn't like it he didn't like
any other class that started being
taught he didn't like the teachers Aaron
really knew like how to get information
he was like I don't need to go to this
teacher to learn how to do geometry I
can just read the geometry book and I
don't need to go to see teacher to learn
their version of American history like I
have like three historical compilations
here like I could just read them and I'm
not interested in that I'm interested in
the what you know the teachers didn't
know what they were talking about
they're very domineering and controlling
and the homework was kind of a sham and
it was just like you know all the way to
Penn students together and force them to
do busy work and you know I started
reading books about like the history of
education and how this educational
system was developed and you know
alternatives to it in ways that people
could actually learn things as opposed
to just regurgitating facts that
teachers told them and that kind of led
me down this path of questioning things
you know once I questioned the school I
was in there questioned the society that
built the school I questioned the
businesses the schools were training
people for that question the government
that you know set up this whole
structure one of the things he was most
passionate about was copyright
especially in those early days copyright
has always being something of a button
publishing industry and on readers but
it wasn't an excessive but it was a
reasonable institution to have in place
to make sure that people got paid what
and generation experienced was the
collision between this antique copyright
system and this amazing new thing we
were trying to build the internet and
the web these things collided and what
we got was campus he then met Harvard
Law Professor Lawrence Lessig who was
then challenging copyright law in the
Supreme Court a young Aaron Schwartz
flew to Washington to listen to the
Supreme Court hearings I am Aaron Swartz
and I'm here to listen to the why did
you fly out here from Chicago and come
all this way to see the Lessig was also
moving forward with a new way to define
copyright on the Internet
it was called Creative Commons so the
simple idea of Creative Commons is to
give people creators a simple way to
mark their creativity with the freedoms
they intended to carry
so if copyright is all about all rights
reserved
then this is a kind of some rights
reserved that's I want a simple way to
say to you here's what you can do with
my work even if there are other things
which you need to get my permission
before you could too
and Aaron's role was the computer part
like how do you architect the licenses
so it would be simple and understandable
or expressed in a way that machines
could process it people are like why do
you have this you know 15 year old kid
writing the specifications for located
comments like don't you think that's a
huge mistake and learnings like the
biggest mistake we would have is not
listening to this kid
you barely is not even tall enough like
that over the podium so this
embarrassing thing where once he put his
screen up nobody could see his face I
was floored just completely
flabbergasted that these adults regarded
him as an adult
and Aaron stood up there in front of a
whole audience full of people and just
started talking about the platform that
he created for Creative Commons and they
were all listening to him just I was
sitting at the back thinking he's just a
kid why are they listening to him but
they did well I don't think I
comprehended it fully though critics
have said it does little to ensure
artists get paid for their work the
success of Creative Commons has been
enormous currently on the website Flickr
allowed over 200 million people used
some form of Creative Commons license he
contributed through his technical
abilities and yet it was not simply a
technical matter to him Aaron often
wrote candidly of his personal blog I
think deeply about things
and I want others to do likewise I work
for ideas and learn from people I don't
like excluding people I'm a
perfectionist but I won't let that get
in the way of publication except for
education and entertainment I'm not
going to waste my time on things that
won't have an impact I try to be friends
with everyone but I hate when you don't
take me seriously I don't hold grudges
it's not productive but I learned from
my experience I want to make the world a
better place
in 2004 Swartz leaves Highland Park and
enrolls in Stanford University he had
had all sort of colitis which was very
troubling and we were concerned about
him taking his medication
he got hospitalized and he would take
this cocktail of pills every day and one
of those pills was a steroid which
stunted his growth and made him feel
different from any of the other students
Aaron I think shows up at Stanford ready
to do scholarship and finds himself in
effectively a babysitting program for
overachieving high-schoolers who in four
years are meant to become
you know captains of industry and
one-percenters and like I think just it
just made him bananas in 2005 after only
one year of college
Schwartz was offered a spot at a new
startup incubation firm called Y
Combinator led by Paul Graham he's like
hey I have this idea for a website and
Paul Graham likes him enough and says
yeah sure Cernan drops out of school
moves to this apartment so this used to
be Aaron's when he moved here so my
father telling me how difficult it was
to get a lease cause Aaron had no credit
and he dropped out of college Aaron
lived in what's now the living room and
some of the posters are left over from
one there and lived here and then the
library there are more books but a lot
of them are aaron's
Aaron's Y Combinator sign was called
infogami a tool to build websites but
infogami struggles to find users and
Schwartz eventually merges his company
with another Y Combinator project in
need of help it was a project headed by
Steve Huffman and Alexis Ohanian called
reddit there we were starting from
almost nothing no users no money no code
and growing day by day into a hugely
popular website and it showed no signs
of letting up first we had a thousand
users the 10,000 and 20,000 and on and
on it's just incredible reddit becomes
huge and it's a real sort of geeky
corner of the internet there's a lot of
humor there's a lot of art and there's
just people who flock to the site and
make that site the main site they go to
every morning to get their news
reddit kind of just borders on on chaos
at some level so on the one hand it's a
place where people discuss news of the
day technology politics and issues and
yet there is a lot of kind of not safe
for work material offensive material
there are some subreddits where trolls
find a welcome home and so in that sense
reddit has been kind of home to
controversy as well it kind of sits on
that edge of chaos when it catches the
attention of the corporate magazine
giant condé Nast who makes an offer to
buy the company some large amount of
money large enough that my dad was
getting bugged with questions about like
how do I store this money like a lot of
like a lot of money like probably more
than a million dollars but I don't
actually know and he's how old 19 20
so it was in this apartment they like
sat around on what predated these
couches hacking on Reddit and when they
sold reddit they added they threw a
giant party and then all flew out to
California the next day and left the
keys with me it was funny you know he
just always thought up so we all kind of
presumed you as the richest person
around but he he said I'll and I'll take
this tiny little shoebox-sized room
that's all I made like it was barely
larger than a club it the idea of him
spending his money on fancy objects just
seemed so implausible
he explains it's like I like living in
apartments so I'm not gonna spend a lot
of money on a new place to live I'm not
gonna buy a mansion and I like wearing
jeans and a t-shirt so I'm not gonna
spend any more money on clothes so like
it's you know really no big deal
what is a big deal to Swartz is how
traffic flows on the internet and what
commands our attention in the old system
of broadcasting you're fundamentally
limited by the amount of space in the
airwaves you know you could only send
out ten channels over the airwaves a
television right or even with cable you
had 500 channels on the internet
everybody can have a channel everyone
can get a blog or a MySpace page
everyone has a way of expressing
themselves and so what you see now is
not a question of who gets access to the
airwaves it's a question of who gets
control over the ways you find people
you know you start seeing power
centralizing in sites like Google these
sort of gatekeepers that tell you where
on the internet you want to go the
people who provide you your sources of
news and information so it's not you
know only certain people have a license
to speak now everyone has a license to
speak it's a question of who gets heard
[Applause]
after he started working in San
Francisco at condé nast
he comes into the office and they want
to give him a computer with all this
crap installed on it and say that he
can't install any new things on his
computer which to developers outrageous
right from the first day he was
complaining about all this stuff gray
walls gray desks gray noise the first
day I showed up here I simply couldn't
take it my lunchtime I had literally
locked myself in a bathroom stall and
started crying I can't imagine staying
sane someone buzzing in my ear all day
let alone getting any air control work
done nobody else seems to get work done
here either everybody's always coming
into our room to hang out and chat or
invite us to play the new videogame
system that wired is testing here but we
had different aspirations that were
politically oriented
and Silicon Valley just doesn't really
quite have that culture that Orient's
technical activity for the purposes of
political goals Aaron hated working for
a corporation they all hate working for
condé Nast but Aaron is like the only
one who's not going to take it and Aaron
basically gets himself fired by not
showing up to work ever
it was said to be a messy breakup both
Alexis Ohanian and Steve Huffman
declined to be interviewed for this film
he rejected the business world one of
the really important things to remember
about that choice when Aaron decided to
kind of leave startup culture is that he
was also leaving behind the things that
had made him famous and well-loved and
you know he was at risk of letting down
fans he got to where he was supposed to
be going and had the self-awareness and
the orneriness to realize that he had
climbed the mountain of [__] to pluck
the single rose and discovered that he'd
lost a sense of smell and rather than
sit there and insist that it wasn't as
bad as it seemed and and he did get the
rose in any event he climbed back down
again
which is pretty cool the way Aaron
always saw it is that programming is
Magic the great you can accomplish these
things that normal humans can't by being
able to program so if you had magical
powers would you use them for good or to
make you mountains of cash
Schwartz was inspired by one of the
visionaries he had met as a child the
man who had invented the world wide web
Tim berners-lee in the 1990s berners-lee
was arguably sitting on one of the most
lucrative inventions of the 20th century
but instead of profiting from the
invention of the world
web he gave it away for free it is the
only reason the world wide web exists
today Aaron is certainly deeply
influenced by Tim Tim is certainly a
very prominent early internet genius who
doesn't in any sense cash out it's not
at all interested in how he's going to
figure out how to make a billion dollars
people will see now there's money to be
made there for the rosula who would have
been lots of little webs instead of one
big one and one little web also so web
doesn't work because you can't follow
links one or the other you know you had
to have the critical mass where the
thing was in tapped out so it's not
gonna work unless the whole planet can
get onboard
community you know feel very strongly
that it's not enough to just live in the
world as it is to just kind of take what
you're given and you know follow the
things that adults told you to do and
the you know your parents told you to do
and that society tells you to do I think
you should always be questioning you
know I take this very scientific
attitude that everything you've learned
is just provisional but you know it's
always open to recantation or refutation
or questioning and I think the same
applies to society once I realized that
there were real serious problems
fundamental problems that I could do
something to address I didn't see a way
that to forget that I didn't see a way
not to we just started spending a lot of
time just kind of as friends we would
just talk for hours into the night I
definitely should have understood that
he was flirting with me I think to some
degree I was like this is a terrible
idea and impossible and therefore I will
pretend it is not happening as my
marriage is breaking down and I was
really stuck without anywhere to go we
became roommates and brought my daughter
over we moved in and furnished a house
and it was really peaceful like my life
had not been peaceful for a while and
really neither had his
[Music]
we were extremely close from the
beginning of our romantic relationship
we just we were in constant contact but
we're both really difficult people to
deal
in a very Ally McBeal discussion he
confessed he had a theme song and I made
him play it for me
it was extraordinary machine by Fiona
Apple I think it was just that sense of
kind of being a little bit embattled
that the song has and it also had like
this hopefulness to it being
uncomfortable so I can't stop changing
all the time in many ways Erin was
tremendously optimistic about life even
when he didn't feel it he could be
tremendously optimistic about life
[Music]
Forte's threw his energy into a string
of new projects involving access to
public information including an
accountability website called watchdog
net and a project called the open
library so the open library project is a
website even visited openlibrary.org and
the idea is to be a huge wiki an
editable website with one page per book
so forever every book ever published we
want to have a web page about it that
combines all the information for
publishers from booksellers from
libraries from readers onto one site and
then gives you links where you can buy
it you can borrow it or you can browse
it I love libraries you know I'm the
kind of person who goes to a new city
and immediately seeks out the library
and that's the dream of open library is
building this website where both you can
leap from book to book from person to
author from subject to idea go through
this vast tree of knowledge that's been
embedded and lost in big physical
libraries that's hard to find it's not
very well accessible in one is really
important because books are our cultural
legacy you know books are the place
people go to write things down and to
have all that swallowed up by one
corporation
this kind of scary how can you bring
public access to the public domain it
may sound obvious that you'd have public
access to public domain but if the fact
it's not true so the public domain
should be free to all but it's often
locked up there's often no guard cages
it's like having a national park but
with a moat around it and gun turrets
pointed to out in case somebody might
want to actually come and enjoy the
public domain one of the things Aaron
was particularly interested in is
bringing public access to the public
domain is one of the things that got him
into so much trouble
I had been trying to get access to
federal court records in the United
States what I discovered was a puzzling
system called pacer which stands for
public access to court electronic
records I started googling and that's
when I ran across Carl Malamud access to
legal materials in the United States is
a 10 billion dollar per year business
pacer is just this incredible
abomination of government service it's
ten cents a page it's it's this most
brain-dead code you've ever seen you
can't search it you can't bookmark
anything you got to have a credit card
and these are public records it's it's
you know US district courts are very
important that's where a lot of our
seminal litigation starts you know civil
rights cases patent cases all sorts of
stuff and journalists and students and
citizens and lawyers all need access to
pacer and it fights them every step of
the way people without means can't see
the law as readily as people that have
that gold American Express card it's
it's a poll tax on access to justice you
know the law is the operating system of
our democracy and you have to pay to see
it
you know that's not much of a democracy
they make about a hundred and twenty
million dollars a year on the Pacer
system and it doesn't cost anything near
that according to their own records in
fact it's illegal the e-government Act
of 2002 states that the courts may
charge only to the extent necessary in
order to reimburse the costs of running
pacer
[Music]
as the founder of public.resource.org
Malamud wanted to protest the Pacer
charges he started a program called the
Pacer recycling project where people
could upload pacer documents they had
already paid for to a free database so
others could use them the Pacer people
were getting a lot of a lot of flack
from Congress and others about public
access and so they put together this
system in 17 libraries across the
country there was free pacer access you
know that's that's one one library every
22,000 square miles I believe so it
wasn't like really convenient I
encouraged volunteers to join the
so-called thumb drive Corps and download
Doc's from the public access libraries
upload them to the Pacer recycling
people take a thumb drive into one of
these libraries and they download a
bunch of documents and they send them to
me I mean it was just a joke in fact
when you clicked on thumb drive Corps
there was a wizard of odd as you know
the Munchkin singing video came up but
of course I get this phone call from
Steve Shelton and Erin saying gee we'd
like to join the thumb drive Corps
around that time I ran into Erin at a
conference this is something that really
has to be a collaboration between a lot
of different people so I approached him
and I said hey I'm thinking about an
intervention on the Pacer problem
[Music]
shelfs had already developed a program
that could automatically download pacer
documents from the trial libraries
Swartz wanted to take a look so I showed
him the code and I didn't know what
would come next but as it turns out over
the course of the next few hours at that
conference he was off sitting in a
corner improving my code recruiting a
friend of his that lived near one of
these libraries to go into the library
and to begin to test his improved code
at which point the folks at the courts
realized something's not going quite
according to plan
data started to come in and come in and
come in and soon there were 760
gigabytes of pacer Doc's about 20
million pages using information
retrieved from the trial libraries
Swartz was conducting massive automated
parallel downloading of the Pacer system
he was able to acquire nearly 2.7
million federal court documents almost
20 million pages of text I'll grant you
that 20 million pages had perhaps
exceeded the expectations of the people
running the pilot access project but
surprising a bureaucrat isn't illegal
Aaron and Carl decided to go talk to the
New York Times about what happened they
also caught the attention of the FBI who
began to stake out Swartz's parents
house in Illinois but I get a tweet from
his mother saying call me so I can find
out what the hell's going on here
and so I finally got ahold of Aaron and
you know Aaron's mother was like oh my
god FBI FBI FBI
an FBI agent drives down to our homes
driveway trying to see if air in his
like in his room
I remember being home that day and
wondering why this car was driving down
our driveway and just driving back out
that's weird like five years later I
read this FBI file and I'm like oh my
goodness was the FBI agent in my
driveway it's terrified he was totally
terrified he was way more terrified
after the the FBI actually called him up
on the phone and tried to sucker him
into coming down to a coffee shop
without a lawyer he said he went home
and laid down on the bed and you know
was shaking the downloading also
uncovered massive privacy violations in
the court documents ultimately the
courts were forced to change their
policies as a result and the FBI closed
their investigation without bringing
charges to this day I find it remarkable
that anybody even at the most remote
podunk field office of the FBI thought
that a fitting use for taxpayer dollars
was investigating people for criminal
theft on the grounds that they had made
the law public how can you call yourself
a lawman and think that there can
possibly be anything wrong in this whole
world with making the law
Aaron was willing to put himself at risk
for the causes that he believed that
bothered by wealth disparity Schwartz
moves beyond technology in into a
broader range of political causes I went
into Congress and I invited him to come
and hang out an intern for us for a
while so that he could learn you know
the political process he was sort of
learning about a new community a new set
of skills and kind of learning to hack
politics it seems ridiculous that miners
should have to hammer away until their
whole bodies are dripping with sweat
faced with the knowledge that if they
dare to stop they won't be able to put
food on the table that night while I get
to make larger and larger amounts of
money each day just by sitting and
watching TV but apparently the world is
ridiculous
so I co-founded a group called the
progressive change campaign committee
and what we try and do is we try and
organize people over the Internet who
care about progressive politics and
moving the country in a more progressive
direction to kind of come together join
our email list join our campaigns and
help get progressive candidates elected
all across the country the group is
responsible for igniting the grassroots
effort behind the campaign to elect
Elizabeth Warren to the Senate he might
have thought it was a dumb system but he
came in and he said I need to learn this
system because it can be manipulated
like any you know like any social system
but his passion for knowledge in
libraries didn't take a backseat Aaron
began to take a closer look at
institutions that publish academic
journal articles by virtue of being
students at a major u.s. University I
assume that you have access to a wide
variety of scholarly journals pretty
much every major university in the
United States pays these sort of
licensing fees organizations like JSTOR
and Thomson and I sigh to get access to
scholarly journals that the rest of the
world can't read these scholarly
journals and articles are essentially
the entire wealth of human knowledge
online
and many have been paid for with
taxpayer money or with government grants
but to read them you often have to pay
again handing over steep fees to
publishers like Reed Elsevier these
licensing fees are so substantial that
people who are studying in India instead
of studying in the United States don't
have this kind of access they're locked
out from all of these journals they're
locked out from our entire scientific
legacy I mean a lot of these journal
articles they go back to the
Enlightenment every time someone has
written down a scientific paper it's
been scanned digitized input may use
collections that is a legacy that has
been brought to us by the history of
people doing interesting work the
history of scientists it's a legacy that
should belong to us as a Commons as a
people but instead it's been locked up
and put online by a handful of
for-profit corporations who then try and
get the maximum profit they can out of
it so a researcher paid by the
university or the people publishes a
paper and in the very very last step of
that process after all the work is done
after all the original researchers and
the thinking the lab work the analysis
after everything is done at that last
stage then the researcher has to hand
over his or her copyright to this
multi-billion dollar company
and it's sick it's an entire economy
built on volunteer labor and then the
publishers said at the very top and
scrape off the cream talk about a scam
one publisher in in Britain made a
profit of three billion dollars last
year I mean what a racket
JSTOR is just a very very small player
in that story but for some reason JSTOR
is the player that Aaron decided to
confront he'd gone to some conference
around open access and open publishing
and I don't know who the person from
Kayseri was but I think they had someone
Aaron asked the question like how much
would it cost to open up JSTOR in
perpetuity and they gave some I think is
200 million dollars something that Aaron
thought was totally ridiculous working
on a fellowship at Harvard he knew users
on mi t--'s famously open and fast
Network next door had authorized access
to the riches of JSTOR Schwartz saw an
opportunity you have a key to those
gates and with a little bit of shell
script magic you can get those journal
articles on September 24 2010 Swartz
registered a newly purchased Acer laptop
on the MIT Network under than
Gary host the client name was registered
as ghost laptop
he doesn't hack JSTOR in the traditional
sense of hacking the JSTOR database was
organized so it was completely trivial
to figure out how you could download all
the articles in JSTOR because it was
basically number it was basically no
slash slash slash number article four
hundred and forty-four thousand 24 and
25 and 26 he wrote a python script all
to keep grabbing dot pi which was keep
grabbing 102 go after another the next
day ghost laptop begins grabbing
articles but soon the computer's IP
address is blocked for schwarz it's
barely a bump in the road he quickly
reassigns his computer's IP address and
keeps it downloading
well JSTOR and MIT take a number of
steps to trying to interfere with this
when they notice that this is happening
and when the more modest steps don't
work then a certain stage they JSTOR
just cuts off MIT from having access to
the JSTOR database so this is kind of
cat-and-mouse game around getting access
to the JSTOR database Aaron ultimately
obviously is the can because he has more
technical capability than the JSTOR
database people do and defending them
eventually there was an unlocked supply
closet in the basement of one of the
buildings they went instead of going
through Wi-Fi he went down there and he
just plugged his computer directly into
the network and just left it there with
an external hard drive downloading these
articles to the computer unknown to
Swartz his laptop and hard drive had
been found by authorities they didn't
stop the downloads instead they
installed a surveillance camera
they found the computer in this room in
the basement of an MIT building they
could have unplugged it they could have
waited for the guy to come back and said
dude what are you doing you know cut it
out
who are you and they could have done all
that kind of stuff but they didn't what
they wanted to do was film it to gather
evidence to make a case that's the only
reason you've filmed something like that
[Music]
at first the only person caught on the
glitchy surveillance camera was using
the closet as a place to store bottles
and cans
[Music]
but days later it caught Swartz
Swartz is replacing hard drive he takes
it out of his backpack leans out of
frame for about five minutes and then
leaves
[Music]
and then they like organized like a
stakeout where as he was biking home
from MIT these cops came out for like
either side of the road or something
like that and started going after it
he describes that he was pressed down
and assaulted by the police he tells me
that they unclear that they were police
that were after him he thought that
someone was trying to attack him
he does tell me they beat him up I was
just devastated the notion of any kind
of criminal prosecution anyone in our
family or anything was so foreign and
incomprehensible I didn't know what to
do well they execute search warrants
said at Aaron's house is apartment in
Cambridge in its office at Harvard
two days before the arrest the
investigation had gone beyond JSTOR and
the local Cambridge police they had been
taken over by the United States Secret
Service the Secret Service began
investigating computer and credit-card
fraud in 1984 but six weeks after the
attack on 9/11 their role expanded
President Bush used the Patriot Act to
establish a network of what they called
electronic Crimes Task Forces the bill
before me takes account of the new
realities and dangers posed by modern
terrorists according to the Secret
Service they are primarily engaged in
activity with economic impact organized
criminal groups or use of schemes
involving new technology the secret
service turned Swartz's case over to the
Boston US Attorney's Office there was a
guy in the US Attorney's Office who had
the title head of the Computer Crimes
Division or task force I don't know what
else he had going but you're certainly
not much of a computer crimes prosecutor
without a computer crime to prosecute so
he jumped on it kept it for himself
didn't assign it to someone else within
the office for the unit and that Steve
Weiman prosecutor Stephen Heymann has
been largely out of public view since
the arrest of Aaron Swartz but he can be
seen here in an episode of the
television show American greed filmed
around the time of Aaron's arrest he is
describing his previous case against the
notorious hacker Alberto Gonzalez a case
that garnered Heymann enormous press
attention and accolades Gonzalez
masterminded the theft of over a hundred
million credit card and ATM numbers the
largest such fraud in history here hyman
describing Gonzalez gives his view on
the hacker mindset
these guys are driven by a lot of the
same things that we're driven by it they
have an ego they like challenge and of
course they like money and everything
you can get from money one of the
suspects implicated in the Gonzalez case
was a young hacker named Jonathan James
believing Gonzalez's crimes would be
pinned on him James committed suicide
during the investigation in an early
press release describing the
government's position in the case of
Aaron Schwartz hymens boss US Attorney
for the District of Massachusetts Carmen
Ortiz said this stealing is stealing
whether you use a computer command or a
crowbar than whether you take documents
data or dollars it's not true it's
obviously not true I'm not saying it's
harmless and I'm not saying that we
shouldn't criminalize stealing of
information but you've got to be much
more subtle and trying to figure out
exactly which kinds of harm's are
harmful here so the thing about a
crowbar is every time I break into a
place with a crowbar I do damage there's
no doubt about it but when Aaron writes
a script that says download download
download a hundred times and second um
there's no obvious damage to anybody if
he does that for the purpose of
gathering archive to do academic
research on it there is never any damage
to anybody he wasn't stealing he wasn't
selling what he got were giving it away
he was making a point for as far as I
could tell the arrests took its toll on
Swartz he just wouldn't talk about it
and he's like very stressed if you
thought like the FBI was like going to
come to your doorstep any day any time
you went down the hall even to do your
laundry and they would break into your
apartment because you left the door
unlocked like I'd be pretty stressed and
it was clear and so Aaron was always
sort of like in like a dour
[Music]
do you wouldn't give off any sensitive
information about his whereabouts during
this time because he was so afraid that
the FBI would be waiting for him
it was a time of unprecedented social
and political activism Time magazine
would later name as their 2011 Person of
the Year the protester there was a kind
of hotbed of hacker activity going on
WikiLeaks had released a trove of
diplomatic cables Manning had been under
arrest at the time it was unknown
whether he was the source of the week
Anonymous which is a kind of protest
ensemble that has a lot of hackers and
its ranks we're going on various sprees
of sorts if you compare that to what he
did this stuff should have been left
behind for MIT and JSTOR to deal with in
a kind of private professional matter it
should have never gotten the attention
of the criminal system it just didn't
belong there
[Music]
before he was indicted Schwartz was
offered a plea deal that involved three
months in prison time in a halfway house
and a year of home detention all without
the use of a computer it was on the
condition that Schwartz plead guilty to
a felony here we are we have no
discovery no evidence whatsoever about
what the government's case is and we
have to make this immense decision where
the lawyer is pushing you to do this the
government is giving you a
non-negotiable demand and you're told
that your likelihood of prevailing is
small so whether you're guilty or not
you're better off taking taking the deal
Boston has its own Computer Crimes
Division lots of lawyers probably more
lawyers than they need so you know you
can imagine all sorts of cases or it
would be really hard to prosecute
because you've got some criminals in
Russia or you've got some people inside
of a corporation and are gonna have a
$500 lawyers or $700 an hour lawyers
sitting down against you and then you've
got this case with this kid which is
pretty easy to prove that he did
something and he's already marked
himself as a troublemaker with the FBI
so why not go as tough as you can in
here against that guy it's good for you
the prosecutor it's good for the
Republic cause you're fighting all those
terrorist types I was so scared I was so
scared of having my computer seized I
was so scared of going to jail because
of my computer being seized
I had confidential material from from
sources from my previous work on my
laptop and that is above all my priority
is to keep my sources safe I was so
scared of what was gonna happen to ADA
Aaron told me that they'd offered in a
deal
and he finally just said that he would
take it if I told him to and I see I
came real close to saying take it
he had these he had developed like
serious political aspirations in the
intervening time between when you know
that moment when he ended that
entrepreneurial startup life and begun
this new life that had come to this
political activism and he just didn't
believe that he could continue in his
life with a felony you know he said to
me one day we were walking by the White
House and he said to me they don't let
felons work there
[Music]
and you know he really he really wanted
that to be his life he hadn't killed
anybody didn't hurt anybody yet like
stolen money hidden anything that seemed
felony worthy right and there is this
idea of it like there's no reason that
he should be labeled a felon and taken
away his right to vote in many states
for doing what he did like that's just
outrageous like it makes sense for him
to be you know maybe find a bunch of
money or you know asked not to come back
to MIT again but like to be a felon to
face jail time
Schwartz turned down the plea deal Hyman
were doubled his efforts Hyman continued
to press us at all at all levels even
with the physical evidence seized from
Aaron's Acer computer hard drive and USB
Drive the prosecutors needed evidence of
his motives why was Aaron Schwartz
downloading articles from JSTOR and just
what did he plan to do with them the
government claims that he was planning
to publish these we don't really know
whether that was his real intention
because Aaron also had a history of
doing projects where he'd analyze giant
data sets of articles in order to learn
interesting things about them the best
evidence for that was that when he was
at Stanford he also downloaded the whole
Westlaw legal database in a project with
Stanford Law Students Swartz had
downloaded the Westlaw legal database he
uncovered troubling connections between
funders of legal research and favorable
results he did this amazing analysis of
for-profit companies giving money to law
professors who wrote Law Review articles
which were then beneficial to like Exxon
during an oil spill right so it was a
very corrupt system of fun
you know vanity research Schwartz had
never released the Westlaw documents in
theory could have been doing the same
thing about the JSTOR database that
would have been completely okay if he
were on the other hand intending to
create a competitive service to JSTOR
we're gonna set up our own you know
access to the Harvard Law Review and
charge you know money for it then you
know okay now it seems like criminal
violation because you're commercially
trying to exploit this material but it's
kind of crazy to imagine that's what he
was doing so but then there's the middle
case well what if he was just trying to
liberate it for all of the developing
world but depending on what he was doing
it creates a very different character to
how the law should be thinking about it
the government was prosecuting him in as
if this was like a commercial criminal
violation like stealing a whole bunch of
credit card records that was that kind
of crime I don't know what he was gonna
do with that database but I heard from a
friend of his that Aaron had told him he
was gonna analyze the data for evidence
of corporate funding of climate change
research that led to biased results and
I I totally believe that
[Music]
I always just told that Steve wanted to
talk to me and I thought maybe this is
the way I could get out of this just
just exit the situation and I didn't
want to live in fear of having my
computer seized I didn't want to live in
fear of having to go to jail on a
contempt of court charge if they tried
to compel me to do it and decrypted my
computer when they came to me and said
you know Steve wants to talk to you that
seemed reasonable they offered Norton
what is known as a queen for a day
letter or a proffer it allowed
prosecutors to ask questions about
Aaron's case Norton would be given
immunity from prosecution herself for
any information she revealed during the
meeting I didn't like it I I told my
lawyers repeatedly that I didn't just
seemed fishy I didn't like this I didn't
want immunity I didn't need immunity I
hadn't done anything but they were
really really stringent that there was
they did not want me meeting the
prosecutor without immunity write a
proper letter basically so there wasn't
handing information over it was at least
that's not how I saw it it was just
having a discussion having an interview
with those they're asking me questions
right I really write and I repeatedly
tried to go in naked I repeatedly I
repeatedly tried to turn down the
proffer letter I was ill I was being
pressured by my lawyers I was confused I
was not doing well by this point I was
depressed and I was scared and I didn't
understand the situation I was in I had
no idea why I was in this situation I
hadn't done anything
interesting much less wrong we went out
of our minds
Aaron was clearly very distraught about
it we were very distraught about Aaron's
attorneys were very distraught about it
we tried to get Quinn to change
attorneys it was very unused to being in
a room with large men well-armed that
are continually telling me I'm lying and
that I must have done something I told
them that this thing that they were
prosecuting wasn't a crime I told them
that they were on the wrong side of
history
I used that phrase I said you're on the
wrong side of history and they looked
bored they even look angry they just
look bored
and it began to occur to me that we
weren't having the same conversation I
mean I told them plenty of things about
you know why people would download
journal articles and eventually I don't
remember what was around it
I mentioned that he'd done this blog
post the guerilla open access manifesto
this is the guerilla open access
manifesto supposedly written in July
2008 in Italy information is power but
like all power there are those who want
to keep it for themselves the world's
entire scientific and cultural heritage
published over centuries and books and
journals is increasingly being digitized
and locked up by a handful of private
corporations meanwhile those who have
been locked out are not standing idly by
you've been sneaking through holes and
climbing over fences liberating the
information locked up by the publishers
and sharing them with your friends but
all this action goes on in the dark in
underground it's called stealing or
piracy as if sharing a wealth of
knowledge were the moral equivalent of
plundering a ship and murdering its crew
but sharing isn't immoral it's a moral
imperative only those blinded by greed
would refuse to let a friend make a copy
there's no justice in following unjust
laws it's time to come into the light
and in the grand tradition of civil
disobedience declare our opposition to
this private theft of public culture the
manifesto itself was allegedly written
by four different people and also edited
by Norton but it was Schwartz who had
signed his name to it when it's over I
go immediately to Aaron and tell him
everything I can remember about it and
he gets very angry the things that I
done shouldn't have added up that way I
hadn't done anything wrong and
everything had gone wrong but I was
never
[Music]
I'm still angry I'm still angry try your
best with these people to do the right
thing
and they turn everything against you and
they will hurt you with anything they
can and in that moment I regret that I
said what I did but my much larger
regret is that we have satellites
that we are okay with us and we are okay
with a justice to the system that tries
to game people into little traps so they
can ruin their lives so yeah I wish I
hadn't said that but I'm much much
angrier that this is where I am
that this is what we as the people think
is okay they used every method that I
think they could think of to get her to
provide information which would be
unhelpful to Aaron and helpful to the
prosecution of Aaron but but you know I
don't think she had information that was
helpful to to to the government months
go by as Schwartz's friends and family
await a looming indictment in the
meantime Schwartz was becoming a go-to
expert on a series of Internet issues
you then do you think that the Internet
is something that should be considered a
human right and something that the
government cannot take away from you yes
definitely I mean this notion that
national security is an excuse to shut
down the Internet
that's exactly what we heard and Egypt
in Syria and all these other countries
and so yeah it's true sites like
WikiLeaks are going to be putting up
some embarrassing material about what
the US government does and people are
gonna be organizing to protest about it
and try and change their government you
know and that's a good thing that's what
all these First Amendment rights a free
expression and freedom of association
are all about and so the notion that we
should try and shut those down I think
just goes against very basic American
principles the principle I think is one
that our founding fathers would have
understood if the internet had been
around back then instead of putting post
offices in the Constitution they would
have put ISPs well it's definitely
interesting to see how shorts meets
activist Taren stinebrickner-kauffman
and the two begins a date we had a
massive global public outcry
there's no okay it won't create any
change you know for people in this city
should cause a massive global public
outcry you know we need a petition
signer
without telling her specifics he warned
her he was involved in something he
called simply the bad thing and I had
sort of crazy theories like that he was
having an affair with Elizabeth Warren
or something I speculated both Hillary
Clinton and Elizabeth Warren actually so
sometime in probably late July Aaron
called me
and I happen to pick up and he said you
know the bad thing might be in the news
tomorrow do you want me to tell you or
do you want to read about it in the news
and I said what I wanted why'd you tell
me here and he said well I've been I've
been arrested for downloading too many
academic journal articles and they want
to make an example out of me and I was
like that's it that's the big fuss
really doesn't sound like a very big
deal on July 14 2011 federal prosecutors
indict Schwartz on four felony counts he
gets indicted on the same day that like
two people in England who are part of
LulzSec get arrested and like a few
other real hackers and err initials like
someone who kind of looks like a cur
enough that they can like you know put
his head on mistake and like put it on
the gates Aaron went to surrender and
they arrested him they then strip
searched him took away his shoelaces
took away his bail and left him in
solitary confinement the district of
Massachusetts United States Attorney's
Office released a statement saying
Schwartz faces up to 35 years in prison
to be followed by three years of
supervised release restitution
forfeiture and a fine of up to
$1,000,000 he is released on $100,000
bail the same day the primary victim in
the case JSTOR formally drops all
charges against shorts and declines to
pursue the case JSTOR but they weren't
our friends they weren't helpful or
friendly to us but they also were just
kind of like we're not part of this
JSTOR and their parent company Ithaka
also sidestepped requests to talk with
this film but at the time they released
a statement saying it was the
government's decision whether to
prosecute not JSTOR's and so it's our
belief that with that the case will be
over that we should be able to get Steve
Heymann to drop the case or settle it in
some rational
when the government refused why well
because I think they wanted to make an
example out of Aaron and they said they
wanted the the reason why they wouldn't
move on requiring a felony conviction
and jail time was that they wanted they
wanted to use this case as a case of
deterrent for deterrence they told us
that they told you yes this was yes he
was yes Steve Hyman said that deterring
who like there's some other people out
there running around logging onto JSTOR
and downloading the articles to make a
political statement I mean who would
they deterring it would be easier to
understand the Obama administration's
posture of supposedly being for
deterrence if this was an administration
that for instance prosecuted arguably
the biggest economic crime that this
country has seen in the last hundred
years the crimes that were committed
that led to the financial crisis on Wall
Street when you start deploying the
non-controversial idea of deterrence
only selectively you stop making a
dispassionate analysis of law-breaking
and you started decided deciding to
deploy law enforcement resources
specifically on the basis of political
ideology and and that's not just
undemocratic it's supposed to be on
America
prosecutor Stephen Heymann later
reportedly told mi t--'s outside counsel
that the straw that broke the camel's
back was a press release sent out by an
organization Swartz founded called
demand progress according to the MIT
account Heymann reacted to the short
statement of support calling it a wild
Internet campaign and a foolish move
that moved the case from a human
one-on-one level to an institutional
level that was a poisonous combination a
prosecutor who didn't want to lose face
who had a political career in the offing
maybe and didn't want to have this come
back and haunt them you spent how many
tax dollars arresting someone for taking
too many books out of the library they
got your ass handed to you in court no
way I then moved to try to put his
pressure on MIT in various ways to get
them to go to the government and request
the government to to stop the
prosecution there doesn't seem to be any
reaction from MIT at that point
mit doesn't defend Aaron which to people
inside of the MIT community seems
outrageous because MIT is a place that
encourages hacking in the biggest sense
of the word at MIT the idea of going and
running around on roofs and tunnels that
you weren't allowed to be in was not
only a rite of passage it was part of
the MIT tour and lock-picking was a
winter course at MIT they had the moral
authority to stop it in its tracks mit
never stood up and took a position of
saying to the feds don't do this we
don't want you to do this zero you're
overreacting this is too strong that I'm
aware of
he acted kind of like a like any
corporation would they they sort of they
they helped the government they didn't
help boss unless they felt they had to
and and they never tried to stop it
mit declined repeated requests to
comment but they later released a report
saying they attempted to maintain a
position of neutrality and believed
Hyman and the US Attorney's Office did
not care what MIT thought or said about
the case MIT is behavior seemed really
at odds with the MIT ethos right you
could argue that MIT turned a blind eye
and that was okay for them to do but
taking that stance taking that neutral
stance in and of itself was taking a pro
prosecutor stance if you look at Steve
Jobs and Steve Wozniak
they started by selling a blue box which
was a thing designed to defraud the
phone company if you look at Bill Gates
and Paul Allen they initially started
their business by using computer time at
Harvard which was pretty clearly against
the rules difference between Aaron and
the people I just mentioned is that
Aaron want to make the world a better
place he didn't just want to make money
Schwartz continues to be outspoken on a
variety of Internet issues you know the
reason the internet works is because of
the competitive marketplace of ideas and
what we need to be focusing on is
getting more information about our
government more accessibility more
discussion more debate but instead it
seems like what Congress is focused on
shutting things down there in thought
you could change the world just by
explaining the world very clearly two
people can literally control your
computer and make it spy on you welcome
Aaron good to have you back on the show
here you know just like spies used to in
olden days put microphones and tap what
people were saying now they're using
computers to do the same things
Schwartz as political activity continues
his attention turning to a bill moving
through Congress designed to curb online
piracy it was called SOPA activists like
Peter Eckersley saw it as an enormous
overreach threatening the technical
integrity of the Internet itself and one
of the first things I did was to call
Aaron I said can we do a big online
campaign against this this isn't a bill
about copyright it's not no you said
it's a bill about the freedom to connect
now I was listening and he thought about
it for a while and then said yes and he
went founded demand progress demand
progress is an online activism
organization we got around a million and
a half members now but started in the
fall of 2010 Aaron was one of the most
prominent people in a community of
people who lead organizing around social
justice issues at the federal level in
this country SOPA was the bill that was
intended to Kurt
Online Piracy of music and movies but
what it did was basically take a
sledgehammer to a problem that needed a
scalpel if passed the law would allow a
company to cut off finances to entire
websites without due process or even to
force Google to exclude their links all
they needed was a single claim of
copyright infringement it pitted the
Titans of traditional media against a
new and now far more sophisticated remix
culture it makes everyone who runs a
website into a policeman and if they
don't do their job of making sure nobody
on their side uses it for anything
that's even potentially illegal the
entire site can get shut down without
even so much as a trial this was
over-the-top I mean this was a
catastrophe this is a serious threat to
speech and civil liberties for all who
use the Internet only a handful of us
who said look we're not for piracy
either but it makes no sense to destroy
the architecture of the internet the
domain-name system and so much that
makes it free and open in the name of
fighting a piracy and aaron got that
right away the freedom is guaranteed in
our Constitution the freedoms our
country had been built on would be
suddenly deleted new technology instead
of bringing us greater freedom would
have snuffed out fundamental rights we'd
always taken for granted and I realized
that day talking to Peter but I couldn't
let that happen
when SOPA was introduced in October 2011
it was considered inevitable our
strategy when it first came out was to
hopefully slow the bill down maybe
weaken it a little bit but even we
didn't think that we would be able to
stop this bill
having worked in Washington what you
learn is that typically in Washington
the legislative fights are fights
between different sets of corporate
money interests they're all duking it
out to pass legislation and the fights
that are the closest are when you have
one set of corporate interests against
another set of corporate interests and
they're financially equally matched in
terms of campaign contributions and
lobbying those are the closest ones the
ones that aren't even fights typically
are ones where all the money is on one
side all the corporations are on one
side it's just millions of people on the
other side haven't seen anything like
PIPA and SOPA in all my time in public
service there were more than 40 United
States senators on that bill as
co-sponsors so there were already a long
long way to getting 60 votes to have it
clear all the procedural hoops even
though I began to cut myself it was a
rough period Schwartz and demand
progress were able to marshal enormous
support using traditional outreach
combined with commonly used voice over
IP to make it very easy for people to
call Congress I have never met anybody
else who was able to operate at his
level both on the technological side and
on the campaign strategy side millions
of people contacted Congress and signed
anti-sopa petitions Congress was caught
off guard there was just something about
watching those clueless members of
Congress debate the bill watching them
insist they could regulate the internet
and a bunch of nerds couldn't possibly
stop them I am NOT a nerd I'm just not
enough of a nerd maybe we ought to ask
some nerds what this thing really does
let's have a hearing bring in the Nerds
really nerds
you know I think actually the word
you're looking for is experts to
enlighten you we use the term geek but
we're allowed to use that because we are
geeks the fact that it got as far as it
did without them talking to any
technical experts reflects the fact that
there is a problem in this town I'm
looking for somebody to come before this
body and testify in a hearing and say
this is why they're wrong there used to
be an office that provided Science and
Technology advice and members could go
to them and say help me understand XYZ
and Gingrich killed it he said it was a
waste of money
ever since then Congress has bunch into
the dark ages I don't think anybody
really thought that SOPA could be beaten
including Aaron I think it was worth
trying but it doesn't seem winnable and
I remember maybe a few months later and
I remember him just turning me on being
like I think we might win this I was
like that would be amazing calls to
Congress continued when the domain
hosting site GoDaddy becomes a supporter
of the bill tens of thousands of users
transferred their domain names in
protest within a week a humbled GoDaddy
reverses their position on SOPA when the
Congress people that supported these the
record and movie industries realized
that there was this backlash they kind
of scaled the bill back a little bit you
could see the curve happening you could
see that we were that our arguments were
starting to resonate it was like Aaron
have been like striking a match and it
was being blown out striking another one
was being blown out and finally he'd
like managed to catch enough kindling
that the flame actually caught and then
they turned into this roaring blaze on
January 16
12 the White House issued a statement
saying they didn't support the bill and
then this happened I'm a big believer
that we should be dealing with issues of
piracy and we should deal with them in a
serious way
but this bill is not the right bill when
Jimmy Wales put his support towards
blacking out Wikipedia the number-five
most popular website in the world this
is a website that's on is several
percent of all of the clicks on anywhere
on the Internet Wikipedia went black
then it went black Craigslist went black
phone lines let me have it'll he'll
flat-out melted members of Congress
started rushing to issue statements
retracting their support for the bill
that they were promoting just a couple
days ago within 24 hours the number of
opponents of SOPA in Congress went from
this to this to see if congressmen and
Senators slowly flip sides throughout
the day of the blackout was pretty
unbelievable there was like a hundred
representatives swing and that was when
this part it was for me to believe after
all this we had bought the thing that
everyone said was impossible some of the
biggest companies in the world had
written off as kind of a pipe dream
could happen
we did it
we want this is a historic week in
internet politics maybe American
politics the thing that we heard from
people in Washington DC from post office
on Capitol Hill was they received more
emails and more phone calls on SOPA
blackout day than they'd ever received
about anything I think that was an
extremely exciting moment this was the
moment when the internet had grown up
politically it was exhilarating because
it's hard to believe it actually
happened it's hard to believe a bill
with so much financial power behind it
didn't simply sail through the Congress
and not only did not sail through it
didn't pass them when you come out in
the streets and you March and you yell
and nobody hears you but I'm here to
tell you today you're powerful
[Applause]
so yeah maybe sometimes you feel like
you're not being listened to but I'm
here to tell you that you are you are
being listened to you are making a
difference you can stop this bill if you
don't stop fighting
[Music]
stop sopa
[Applause]
some of the biggest Internet companies
to put it frankly would benefit from a
world in which their little competitors
could get censored we can't let that
happen for him it was more important to
be sure that you made a small change
than to play a small part in a big
change but SOPA was like playing a major
part in a major change and so for him
was kind of as proof of concept like
okay you know what I want to do with my
life has changed the world I think about
it this really scientific way of like
I'm measuring my impact and this shows
that it's possible right the thing that
I want to do with my life is possible I
have proved that I can do it but iron
sports couldn't change the world for a
guy who never really thought he had done
much which was Arab it was one of the
few moments where you could really see
that he felt like he had he had done
something good feeling here is his maybe
one and only victory lap
[Music]
everyone said there was no way we could
stop so much we stopped it does it flee
outrageously good victories and the year
wasn't even over yet
I mean if there's a time to be positive
it's now you know he wins at SOPA year
after he's arrested it's not
unambiguously happy moment there's a lot
going on he's so attuned towards
participating in the political process
you can't stop him the list of
organizations Swartz founded or
co-founded is enormous and years before
Edward Snowden would expose widespread
internet surveillance Swartz was already
concerned it is shocking that thing
could be accountability is so lacks that
they don't even have sort of basic
statistics about how big the spying
program is and if the answer is always
buying on so many people we can't
possibly even count them then that's an
awful lot of people all right you know
one thing if they said look you know we
know the number of telephones were
spying on we don't know exactly how many
real people that corresponds to but they
just came back and said we can't give
you a number at all that's pretty I mean
it's scary it's what it is well that's
scary you know they put incredible
pressure on him took away his you know
his all of the money he had made they
you know threatened to take away his
physical freedom why'd they do it you
know I mean well why why are they going
after whistleblowers you know why are
they going after people who tell the you
know who tell the truth about all sorts
of things I mean it from the bank's to
the you know to war to just sort of
government transparency so secrecy
serves those who are already in power
and we are living in an era of secrecy
that coincides with an era where the
government is doing also a lot of things
that are probably illegal and
unconstitutional so those two things are
not coincidences it's very clear that
this technology has been developed not
for small countries overseas but right
here for use in the United States by the
US government spying program is it's
just sort of long slow expansion you
know going back to the Nixon
administration right obviously it became
big after 9/11 under george w bush and
has continued to expand it the problems
have slowly grown worse and worse but
there's never been this moment you can
point to say okay we need to galvanize
opposition today because today is when
it matters
instead it's matter the prosecution in
my estimation of Aaron Schwartz was
about sending a particular laser-like
message to a group of people that the
Obama administration sees as politically
threatening and that is essentially the
hacker the information and the democracy
activist community and the message that
the Obama administration wanted to send
to that particular community was in my
estimation we know you have the ability
to make trouble for the establishment
and so we are going to try to make an
example out of Aaron Schwartz to scare
as many of you as possible into not
making that trouble and the government
said oh the legal opinions were using to
legalize the spying program are also
classified so we can't even tell you
which laws we're using to spy on you you
know every time they can say oh this is
another instance of cyberwar the cyber
criminals are attacking us again we're
all in danger we're all under threat
they use those as excuses to push
through more and more dangerous laws and
so just to follow up like personally how
how do you feel the fight is going yeah
it's up to you you know the sort of
these two polarizing perspectives right
everything is great the Internet has
created all this freedom and liberty and
everything's gonna be fantastic or
everything is terrible the Internet has
created all these tools for cracking
down and spying and you know controlling
what we say and I think is both are true
right the Internet has done both and
both are kind of amazing and astonishing
and which one will win out in the long
run is up to us it doesn't make sense to
say oh one is doing better than the
other you know they're both true and
it's up to us which ones we emphasize
and which ones we take advantage of
because they're both there and they're
both always going to be there
on September 12 2012 federal prosecutors
filed a superseding indictment against
Swartz adding additional counts of wire
fraud unauthorized access to a computer
and computer fraud now instead of four
felony counts Swartz was facing 13 the
prosecution's leverage had dramatically
increased as did Swartz's potential jail
time and fines
they fathered a separate indictment to
add more charges and they had a theory
about why this conduct constituted a
number of federal crimes and that a very
significant sentence could attach to it
under the law that theory and much of
the prosecution's case against Swartz
involved a law created originally in
1986 it is called the Computer Fraud and
Abuse Act the Computer Fraud of music
was inspired by the movie wargames with
Matthew Broderick which a great movie I
have you now in this movie a kid gets
the ability through the magic of
computer networks to like launch a
nuclear attack
now that's not actually possible and it
certainly was impossible in the 80s but
apparently this movie scared Congress
enough to pass the original Computer
Fraud and Abuse Act this is a law that's
just behind the times for example that
penalizes a Terms of Service kinds of
arrangements you can have something like
eHarmony or match.com and somebody sort
of inflates their own personal
characteristics and all of a sudden
depending on the jurisdiction and the
prosecutors they could be in a whole
host of troubles we all know what terms
of use are most people don't read them
but not abiding by their terms could
meet you are committing a felony the
website Terms of Service often say
things like be nice to each other or
don't do anything that's improper the
idea that the criminal law has anything
to say about these kinds of violations I
think strikes most people is crazy the
examples get even more crazy until it
was changed in March of 2013 the terms
of use on the website of Hurst's
Seventeen magazine said you had to be 18
in order to read it I would say that the
way the CFAA has been interpreted by the
Justice Department we are probably all
breaking the law vague and prone to
misuse the CFAA has become a
one-size-fits-all hammer for a wide
range of computer-related disputes
though not the only factor in his case
11 of the 13 charges against Swartz
involved the Computer Fraud and Abuse
Act the question why hangs over much of
the story of Aaron Swartz just what was
motivating the government and what would
their case have been the Department of
Justice declined requests for answers
but Professor Orin Kerr is a former
prosecutor who has studied the case so I
think I come about this case from a
different direction and other people on
a number of reasons I was a federal
prosecutor at the Justice Department for
three years before I started teaching
the government came forward with an
indictment based on what crimes they
thought were committed just as a purely
lawyers matter looking at the precedents
looking at the statute looking at the
history looking at the cases that are
out there so
Pharr I think it was a fair indictment
based on that you can debate whether
they should have charged this case
there's just a lot of disagreement some
people are on you know the open access
side some people are not I think the
government took Swartz's guerilla open
access manifesto very seriously and I
think they saw him as somebody who was
committed as a moral imperative to
breaking the law to overcome a law that
Swartz saw as unjust and in a democracy
if you think a law is unjust there are
ways of changing that law there's going
to Congress as Swartz did so masterfully
with SOPA or you can violate that law in
a way to try to nullify that law and I
think what was driving the prosecution
was the sense that Swartz was committed
not just to breaking the law but to
really making sure that law was
nullified that everyone would have
access to the database in a way that you
couldn't put the toothpaste back into
the - it would be done and Swartz's side
would win there's a big disagreement in
society as to whether that is an unjust
law and ultimately that's a decision for
the American people to make working
through Congress and then the second
problem is I think we're still trying to
figure out what's the line between less
serious offenses and more serious
offenses we're now entering this
different environment of computers and
computer misuse and we don't yet have a
really strong sense of exactly what
these lines are we're just working that
out
this is a poor use of prosecutorial
discretion the hammer that the Justice
Department has to scare people with
these kids just gets bigger and bigger
and bigger and so most people just you
know you can't roll the dice with your
life like that should we tap somebody's
phone should we film them should we turn
somebody and get them to testify against
these other people that's how federal
agents and prosecutors think they build
cases they make cases Swartz was caught
in the gears of a brutal criminal
justice system that could not turn back
a machine that has made America the
country with the highest rate of
incarceration in the world we have in
this country allowed ourselves to be
captured by the politics of fear and
anger and anything were afraid of like
the future of the Internet and access
and anything we're angry about
instinctively creates a criminal justice
intervention and we've used jail prison
and punishment to resolve a whole host
of problems that historically were never
seen as criminal justice problems the
impulse to threaten indict prosecute
which is part of what has created this
debate and controversy over online
access and information on the Internet
it's very consistent with what we've
seen in other areas the one difference
is is that the people are usually
targeted and victimized by these kinds
of criminal and carceral responses are
typically poor and minority
schwartz is isolation from friends and
family increased he had basically
stopped working on anything else and the
case was in fact like taking over sort
of his whole life one of Aaron's lawyers
apparently told the prosecutors that he
was emotionally vulnerable and that was
something that they really needed to
keep in mind so that they they knew that
it was weighing on him very heavily he
did not like having his actions and his
movements restricted in any way and the
threat of jail which they pounded him
with a lot was terrifying to him
completely exhausted his financial
resources and it cost us a lot of money
also and he raised a substantial amount
of money so it was you know it was in
the millions of dollars yes yes yeah I
think he didn't want to be a burden to
people I think that was a factor like I
have my normal life and then I have this
shitty thing I have to deal with and I
try to like keep the two of them as
separate as possible but they were just
beginning to blur together and
everything was becoming shitty Swartz
faced a tough choice that was only
getting tougher do you admit guilt and
move on with your life or do you fight a
broken system with his legal case the
answer was simple he rejects the final
plea deal and a trial date is set Aaron
was was resolute that he didn't want to
knuckle under and accept something that
he didn't believe was fair but I also
think he was scared
[Music]
I don't think they would have convicted
Aaron I think we would have walked him
out of that courthouse and I would have
given him a big hug and we would have
walked across that Little River in
Boston and gone and had a couple of
beers I really thought that we were
right I thought that we were gonna win
the case I thought that we could win the
case he didn't talk about it very much
but you could see the enormous pain that
he was going through
[Music]
no time in his childhood did Aaron have
any severe mood swings or like
depressive episodes or anything that I
would ascribe to severe depression and
it's possible you know he was the price
people get depressed
[Music]
very early in our relationship like
three or four weeks in or something
remembered him saying to me that I was a
lot stronger than he was you know he was
he was brittle in a lot of ways things
were a lot harder for him and for a lot
of people as part of his brilliance too
I think he probably had something like
clinical depression in his early 20s I
don't think he did when I was with him
he wasn't a joyful person but that's
different from being depressed he's just
under such such an enormous pressure for
two years straight he just didn't want
to do it anymore he was just like I just
think it was too much I got a phone call
late at night I could tell something was
wrong and they like I called and I
realized what had happened a co-founder
of the social news and entertainment
website reddit has been found dead
police say 26 year-old Aaron Swartz
killed himself yesterday in his Brooklyn
apartment
I just thought we've lost one of the
most creative minds of our generation I
was like the whole world fell apart
[Music]
it was a little hard this nights of my
life it's like if screaming I can't hear
you what did you say I can't hear you I
can't that's it
like yeah none of it made any sense and
really still doesn't I was so frustrated
angry you know I tried to explain it to
my kids
my three-year-old told me that the
doctors would fix him I have known lots
of people have died but I've never lost
everybody like this because everybody
feels that I do - there's so much we
could have ordered - like I just didn't
know he was there I didn't know this is
what he was suffering and he was part of
me
[Music]
I just wanted it to not be real and then
and then I just looked at his Wikipedia
page and I saw the end date
[Music]
Aaron is dead Wanderers in this crazy
world we have lost a mentor a wise elder
hackers for right where one down we've
lost one of our own nurturers carers
listeners feeders parents or we have
lost a child yes Philippe
my first thought was what if nobody even
noticed us yeah because I wasn't clear
to me how salient he was I had never
seen anything quite like the outpouring
I saw the net just lit up
and everyone was trying to explain it in
their own way but I've never seen people
grieve on Twitter before people were
visibly grieving online
he was the Internet's own boy and the
old world killed him
we are standing in the middle of a time
when great injustice is not touched
Architects of the financial meltdown
have dinner with the president regularly
the middle of that time the idea that
this was what the government had to
prosecute just see it's absurd if it
weren't tragic the question is can we do
something given what's happened to make
the world a better place and how can we
further that legacy that's the only
question one could ask all over the
world they were starting to be
hackathons gatherings Aaron Schwartz has
some sense brought the best out of us in
trying to say how do we fix this he was
in my humble opinion one of the true
extraordinary revolutionaries that this
country has produced I don't know
whether Aaron was defeated or victorious
but we are certainly shaped by the hand
of the things that he wrestled with
when we turn armed agents of the law on
citizens trying to increase access to
knowledge we've broken the rule of law
we've desecrated the temple of Justice
Aaron Swartz was not a criminal change
does not roll in on the wheels of
inevitability it comes through
continuous struggle Aaron really could
do magic and I'm dedicated to making
sure that his magic doesn't end with his
death he believed that he could change
the world and he was right out of the
last week and out of today chances are
already rising since Swartz's death
representative Zoe Lofgren and Senator
Ron Wyden have introduced legislation
that would reform the Computer Fraud and
Abuse Act the outdated law that formed
the majority of the charges against
shorts it's called Aaron's law Aaron
believed that like you literally ought
to be asking yourself all at the time
what is the most important thing I could
be working on in the world right now if
you're not working on that why aren't
you
[Music]
I wish we could change the past
but we cannot but we can change the
future and we must we must do so for
Aaron we must do so for ourselves we
must do so to make our world a better
place a more humane place a place where
justice works and access to knowledge
becomes a human right so there was a kid
back in February from Baltimore 14 years
old who had access to JSTOR and he'd
been spelunking through JSTOR after
reading something and he figured out a
way to do early tests for pancreatic
cancer and pancreatic cancer kills the
[__] out of you because we detect it way
to light by the time we detect it it's
already too late to do anything about it
and he sent emails off to the entire
oncology department at Johns Hopkins you
know hundreds of them and every 14 14
year-old kid yeah and most of them
ignored it right but one of them like
cinnamon email back and said this is not
an entirely stupid idea when she coming
over this kid worked evenings and
weekends with this researcher in
February I heard him on the news just a
couple of weeks after Aaron died when
Aaron was in the news a lot
[Music]
sorry and he said the reason he was on
the news it's cuz they've done it they
were shipping an early test for
pancreatic cancer that's gonna save
lives and he said this is why what Aaron
did was so important because he never
know right this this truth of the
universe is not only something that
policymakers use to figure out you know
what the speed limit should be it's
where the thing that's gonna keep you
know your kid from dying of pancreatic
cancer comes from and without access the
person who might come up with a thing
that's got your number on it may never
find that answer
[Music]
you